The tale of shinobi...
is the tale of restoring Mother.
I shall now show you two...
I don't have any candy,
(ゼツ)忍の物語は
母が復活するための物語だ。
but the puppet show
is about to begin...
お前たちに見せてやる。
飴玉はないが紙芝居の始まりだ。
aimaina hyouden koshiraete hitatteru no
I create a vague critical biography and wallow in it
seisei saisai nani o mada matteru no
Generation after generation, time after time,
what are you still waiting for
itsunomanika hitori ni natta
I was all alone before I knew it
tameiki hitotsu haite nageite
Breathed out a single sigh and lamented
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosunda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
en de tsunagareba kono hibi mo
Bind these days with bonds and perhaps
suteru hodo koware tenaidarou
They can be salvaged
ayumi o tomenaide
Don't stop walking forward
kibou o sutenaide
Don't give up hope
douka furimuite
Please look back
dou ka kimiyo
Please, if you would
jin jin kokoro ga itamunara
If the heart throbs with pain
kannen no ori o uchiyaburu nda
Break through the ideology that imprisons you
enen tsukihi wa megurukedo
Time goes around for eternity
suteru ni wa yami ga asaidarou
But the darkness within you is still shallow,
not worth throwing it all away
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosu nda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
ai o wakeaeba kono hibi mo
If we love each other then surely these days will
mouichido kimi o terasudarou
Once again, shine upon you
Kaguya Otsutsuki
Look at that!
It's glowing!
It looks suspicious!
What is it?
Is it a star?
That's no star, it's moving!
How terrifying!
Follow it!
Yes, sir!
あれを見ろ。
光ってる。 怪しいぞ。
(テンジ)何だあれは？
星か？
あんな星があるものか！
動いている。
A woman?
追え。
はっ！
And you're saying that
she came from the heavens?
Yes...
This woman appeared in the spot
where the light had fallen.
女…。 この者が
天からやってきたと申すのか？
Be careful!
はい。 光の落ちた場所から
この女が出てきました。
((用心しろ))
Hmm...
What is your name?
Answer him!
The man standing before you is
the King of the Land of Sou,
Lord Tenji!
フム… 名を何と申す？
You there!
The Land of Ka must have
sent this woman to spy on us!
答えぬか！
このお方は祖の国の皇→
Interrogate her and
make her confess!
- Yes, sir!
テンジ様におわせられるぞ！
Wait.
You—!
これ！
恐らくこの女は→
What did you do?!
彼の国の回し者に違いありません。
締め上げて素性を吐かせよ。
はっ。
待て。
What's the matter?
うっ…。
あっ…。
こやつ！
何をした？
My name is Kaguya.
Kagu... ya?
I am the one who protects
the Divine Tree.
うっ…。
どうした？
I have been assigned to
take care of your needs.
(カグヤ)わらわの名は カグヤ。
I am Aino...
カグ… ヤ？
神樹を見守る者。
(アイノ)このたび
カグヤ様のお世話をするよう→
Lady Kaguya?
おおせつかりました
アイノと申します。
Several millennia ago,
that tree appeared out of nowhere
and grew into a massive tree
before our very eyes.
But I have heard
frightening rumors too.
Anyone who approaches it is quickly
consumed by a demon spirit
カグヤ様？
and dies like a withered branch.
あの樹は 数千年前に忽然と生えて
見る間に大木になったとか。
Forgive me for speaking
of such things!
Do not worry.
For it is true...
(アイノ)でも 恐ろしい噂も聞きます。
Huh?
あの樹に近づくと→
And some day...
たちまちのうちに精根が尽き果て
枯れ木のように死んでしまうとか。
Lord Tenji!
Ministers Suzaku and Genbu from
the Land of Ka are here to see you.
あっ！ すみません
よけいなことを言って。
This is the border between
the Land of Ka and the Land of Sou.
気にすることはない。
The issue is this lake.
本当のことです。
(アイノ)えっ？
Presently, this region is said to be
part of the Land of Sou...
それも いつか…。
But an ancient manuscript
was recently discovered.
テンジ様！ 彼の国の スザク大臣と
ゲンブ大臣がお見えになりました。
On it, has been recorded
from time immemorial,
that this land was originally within
the Land of Ka's territory.
(スザク)これは
彼の国と祖の国の国境である。
We wish to have this land
returned to us.
But that lake is our source of water
for our farmlands in the Land of Sou.
問題は この湖。
この地は 現在
祖の国の領地になっておるが→
If I were to return that land...
No matter what situation arises,
こたび 彼の国で発見された
古文書によれば→
to return what was stolen
to its true owner...
古来 彼の国の領地と
記されておる。
is the right thing to do.
(スザク)この地を
我らに返していただきたい。
If we do not receive
a favorable answer,
しかし その湖は
祖の国の農地の水源。
we cannot be responsible
for whatever misfortune
befalls the Land of Sou!
それを貴殿の国へ渡したら…。
(ゲンブ)どのような事情があろうが→
Now, now...
盗んだものは
持ち主に返すべきと存ずる。
I'm sure you will need some time
to prepare and take care of things.
それが物事の道理。
We shall return in a few days
to hear your answer.
よき返事が聞けぬ場合は 祖の国に
どのような災いが降りかかるか…。
By the way,
責任は負えませぬぞ。
I understand you have taken
a celestial maiden as a concubine.
(スザク)まぁ まぁ！
I hear she is indescribably
beautiful and mysterious.
そちらにも いろいろと 事情を
整理する時間が必要でござろう。
I am most curious to see her.
後日 改めて 答えを
伺いにまいることとしましょう。
そういえば テンジ殿は
天女を妾にしたとか。
Without a doubt,
this recently discovered artifact
is a fabrication by the Land of Ka.
(ゲンブ)なんとも言えぬ
神秘的な美しさを持つ美女と→
I am aware of that...
The Land of Ka makes false claims
against neighboring lands
お聞きしたが…。
私も見てみたいものだ！
as a pretext to war.
That's how they've
expanded their lands.
This case is no different.
(ゲンブ/スザク)アハハハハハ！
But they have an army three times
greater than the Land of Sou.
発見された古文書など
おそらく 彼の国のでっちあげ…。
There is no way we can win.
Suzaku and Genbu...
わかっている。
Sending those two
as messengers means...
彼の国は 隣国に因縁をつけては
戦を仕掛け 領土を広げてきた。
The Land of Ka is serious.
We cannot be meek—
今回も同じだ。
Lord Tenji, let's stand up to them!
だが 彼の国の戦力は
我が祖の国の３倍…。
If we are doomed anyway,
let's go down fighting and
show them the pride of the Sou!
戦となれば 勝ち目はない。
Do not panic just yet.
スザクとゲンブ… 彼らを使者として
よこしたところを見ると→
彼の国は本気。 このまま
おめおめと引き下がるとは…。
テンジ様！ 受けて立ちましょうぞ!!
どうせ滅ぶなら
祖の国の意地を見せつけてやる！
Lord Tenji!
そう慌てるな。
What is Kaguya doing?
Lady Kaguya spends her days
looking up at the sky like that.
It's as though she's waiting for
someone to come for her...
テンジ様。
According to the villagers,
they say Lady Kaguya
came from the heavens...
カグヤは何をしておる？
カグヤ様は 毎日 ああやって
空を見上げておいでです。
The thing is... I don't remember
my first encounter with Kaguya.
Oh?
まるで どなたかが ご自分を
お迎えにいらっしゃるかのように。
May I borrow that?
Huh?
Oh this?
(アイノ)村人たちの噂では
カグヤ様は 空からやってきたと…。
それが… カグヤとの出会いは
覚えていないのだ。
You must be freezing, standing in
the cold night air for so long.
は…？
I wonder if that glowing world above
is always beautiful and at peace...
それを借りられぬか？
えっ？ これですか？
A strange feeling comes over me
as I gaze up at the night sky...
The fact that such a beautiful light
lies afloat in pitch darkness...
ずっと 夜風に吹かれていたのでは
寒かろう。
Just what is it?
Will I ever be able to go there?
あの輝く光の世界は
常に美しく穏やかなのだろうか？
(テンジ)こうして 夜空を見上げると
何か 不思議な気がする。
I hear that you gaze up
at the sky every night...
真っ黒な空間に あのような
美しい光が浮かんでいるなんて…。
Are you waiting for someone?
あれは いったい
なんなのだろう？
It's all right if that's the case.
私も いつか そこに行くことが
できるのだろうか とね…。
From now on, whenever you're
lonely and look up at the sky,
I shall be by your side.
そなたは 毎日
空を見つめているそうな。
誰かを待っているのか？
Is there anything that you desire?
たとえ そうであってもいい。
What I wish... is for peace
with no more fighting.
お前が寂しくなって
空を見上げるときには→
私は いつも
隣にいることにしよう。
Peace... huh?
そなたは何か望むものはないか？
わらわが望むのは争いのない平和。
They're from the Land of Ka!
Why that—!
They're messing with us!
平和か…。
Don't!
Can't you see they're just
trying to provoke us?!
Damn it!
あれは 彼の国の…
あんにゃろ ナメやがって！
Lord Tenji!
The mischief caused by
the Land of Ka at our border
やめるんだ！ あいつらが
挑発してるのがわからねえのか。
is growing steadily worse!
クソッ。
Unless we take action...
the farmers' ire will
reach a breaking point!
I understand...
But I forbid you to confront
the Land of Ka.
テンジ様！
But—!
I seek peace.
国境では
彼の国の者たちによる悪さが→
If fighting ensues, many will die.
ますます激しくなっております。
何か手を打たなければ…
すでに民の怒りは限界かと。
We must move forward with peaceful
negotiations with the Land of Ka.
Anyone who makes a move
on the Land of Ka
わかっている。 だが決して→
will be executed on my order.
彼の国の者に手を出してはならぬ。
What is he thinking?
しかし。
私が求めるのは平和だ。
戦になれば 多くの者たちが死ぬ。
彼の国とは和平交渉を進めるのだ。
彼の国の者に手を出した者は
我が名のもとに死罪とする！
なんと…。
Is Lord Tenji here?
Yes...
He comes nearly every night.
It seems Lady Kaguya has come to
accept his presence recently,
and they've been spending more
and more time together.
I didn't ask you for details!
Lord Tenji! Lord Tenji!
ハァ ハァ… テンジ様はおられるか？
What do you want at this hour?
はい 毎日のように
お見えになります。
The Land of Ka is at the border
with a large army!
最近では カグヤ様も
心をお許しになったのか→
What?!
お二人でおられる時間も
ずいぶんと多くなって…。
Kaguya...
I must depart for
the front immediately.
そんなことは聞いとらん！
To war?
テンジ様 テンジ様！
No, this is for peace.
何事だ？ こんな夜中に。
But if things should go wrong...
国境に彼の国の大軍勢が。
Prepare to go into hiding right away!
なに!?
Yes!
Do not worry.
I shall return right away.
カグヤ 私はすぐに
出陣しなければならない。
戦が？
いや あくまで和平のために。
しかし 悪くすると…。
Let's go!
急いで身を隠す準備を。
はい。
Yes!
Guard the castle.
Leave it to us.
心配するな
すぐに戻ってこられる。
我々も行くぞ。
はっ。
館の守りは頼んだぞ。
お任せください。
So that Kaguya has left
the capital of Sou...
This is the perfect opportunity
to capture that woman.
There's no need to rush.
The Land of Sou
will be ours in no time.
It's just one woman...
Be patient.
It's my policy to get what I want
as fast as I can.
ふむ カグヤとやらは
祖の国の都を離れたか。
You're hopeless...
これは この女を手に入れる
好機だな。
Gather skilled men.
We're going after Kaguya.
そう慌てることもなかろう。
Yes, sir!
もうすぐ 祖の国は
我らが手中に収まる。
女一人 そのときで
よいではないか。
欲しいものは一刻も早く
いただくのが私の流儀だ。
好き者め。
手だれの者を集めよ
すぐにカグヤのあとを追う。
はっ。
You can't sleep?
I'll stay with you.
(アイノ)眠れないのですか？
私も お供します。
Enemy attack!
Alert!
Lady Kaguya! Lady Aino!
うっ！
What's going on?
So this is where you were hiding!
Who are you?!
You dare approach knowing that
this lady is Lord Tenji's concubine?!
Tenji?
敵襲だ～ 出合え！
≪キャー！
I'm from the Land of Ka,
why should I care about him?
カグヤ様 アイノ様！
何事です？
The Land of Sou will fall very soon.
To put it bluntly, what belongs to
Tenji will soon belong to me.
(スザク)
こんなところに隠れていたか。
何者です このお方を
テンジ様のご側室と知っての無礼か？
The rumors were right...
such a beauty.
And very refined.
テンジだと？
彼の国の私には関係ないな。
From this moment on, you are mine!
Lady Kaguya, please run!
Lady Kaguya...
Like you can escape!
もう間もなく この国は滅びる。
つまり テンジのものは
私のものということさ。
《スザク : 噂どおりの美貌だな。
それに気品がある》
Lady Kaguya!
今からは私のものだ！
Even in this situation,
you're not scared...
カグヤ様 逃げて カグヤ様！
Well, that just makes me
like you more!
逃げられるか！
Take her!
Do not touch me.
カグヤ様！
ほう この状況でも臆さぬか。
Don't back off!
ますます私の好みよのう。
捕らえよ！
(２人)うわ～！
わらわに触れるな。
ちっ！
So the bewitching beauty
is actually a monster...
ひるむな！
Th-The Land of Sou
is really doomed now...
ああ～！
I would like you to withdraw
your troops immediately.
You seem to be under
the wrong impression, Lord Tenji.
妖艶な正体は化け物であったか。
We are not at war.
こ これで祖の国は
本当に終わりだな。
This army is just to
protect our boundary.
Such a large army just to
protect the boundary is...
I do not intend to wage war either.
早く軍勢を
引き上げていただきたい。
There's proof in the fact that
テンジ殿は何か
勘違いしておるようだな。
I have ordered anyone who draws
his sword against the Land of Ka
to be executed immediately.
これは戦のためではなく
国境を守るための軍勢だ。
Oh, is that so?
Then I want you to execute Kaguya.
国境の守りに
このような大軍勢は…。
This woman known as Kaguya killed
my vassal, and then tried to kill me!
わが国にも
戦の腹積もりはない。
それを証拠に 我が国では
彼の国の者に手を出した者は→
Impossible...
Kaguya would never—!
即刻死罪という命を
出してある。
If you think I'm lying,
ask this woman.
ほう なるほど ならば
カグヤを死罪にしてもらいたい。
Is it true?
Yes.
カグヤと申す者 我が部下を殺し
私も殺そうとしたのだ。
Lady Kaguya...
dispatched the soldiers of Ka
with frightening power...
そんな カグヤが？
Lord Tenji!
Unless you behead Kaguya,
this war will not end!
ウソだと言うなら
この女に聞いてみるがよい。
本当なのか？
I'm leaving.
はい カグヤ様は恐ろしい力で
彼の国の兵たちを。
テンジ殿 カグヤの首なくして
戦は止められませんぞ。
What happened to you?
That woman Kaguya...
is a horrible monster.
Leave the witch-hunt to them...
And in the interim,
we'll conquer everything.
戻るぞ。
その姿 大丈夫か？
カグヤという女
とんだ もののけよ。
Kaguya did this?
化け物退治は ヤツらに任せ
その隙に全てをいただこうぞ。
Whatever the reason,
there seems to be no doubt that
she tried to kill Sir Suzaku.
Kaguya...
What are you going to do,
Lord Tenji?!
Are you really going to
execute Lady Kaguya?
これをカグヤが？
子細はどうあれ→
Unless I give them her head,
war will not be averted...
スザク殿を手にかけようとしたことは
確かなようですな。
Are you really willing to do that?
カグヤ…。
いかがいたしましょう テンジ様。
本当に カグヤ様の首を？
Send all troops after Kaguya...
Leave no stone unturned. Find her.
差し出さなければ→
戦は回避できまい。
I have no other choice...
本当に それでよいのですな？
全軍 カグヤを追うのだ。
Are they...
... pursuers?
草の根を分けてでも捜し出せ。
致し方あるまい。
They're from the Land of Sou!
あれは 追っ手？
So Lord Tenji dispatched them!
Let us hurry.
My fate is with the Divine Tree!
これは祖の国の…。
Lady Kaguya!
それでは 追っ手はテンジ様。
If you explain
what happened to Lord Tenji,
急ぐのです。
わらわの運命は神樹とともに。
I'm certain that he will forgive you...
Lady Kaguya...
My strength...
Lady Kaguya!
Could you be... with child?
カグヤ様 テンジ様に事情を話せば
きっと お許しを…。
This is terrible!
How could Lord Tenji—?!
I must get to the Divine Tree...
Please go...
I will stop them.
くっ…。
カグヤ様。
力が…。
Wait!
Lord Tenji!
Please order your soldiers to retreat!
カグヤ様
もしや お腹に ややこが…。
Lady Kaguya is with...
ひどい！ なのにテンジ様は…。
Aino!
なんとしても神樹に。
行ってください ここは私が。
待って。
テンジ様！ 兵を お引きください。
... with your child, Lord Tenji!
カグヤ様のお腹には…。
Lady Kaguya...
アイノ！
Please bear... a healthy...
Aino!
テンジ様の…。
カグヤ様。
It's now time to destroy
the Land of Sou!
元気な… ややこ…。
Onward!
The Land of Sou will now be ours.
アイノ！
Kaguya...
今こそ 祖の国を滅ぼす機会だ。
押せ～！
これで祖の国は我らのもの。
カグヤ。
Kaguya!
Shine upon the world,
Infinite Tsukuyomi!
カグヤ。
What is this?
この世を照らせ 無限月読。
なんだ？
ぐあ～っ！
Kaguya...
What... are... you?
カグヤ。
I shall rule over this world...
Together with my children.
お前は いったい何者なのだ…。
この地は わらわが治める。
わらわの子たちとともに。
kaze ga fui te iku
The wind is blowing
yoru o mata yorokete aruku
I stagger through the night
butsukatte koron de shippai bakkashite
Colliding, falling, and failing
make sou ni naru kedo
I'm always about to lose
warawaretatte ii yo kanarazu umaku iku sa
Go ahead and laugh, I'll figure out a way
gomen ne datte ieru
I'm even willing to say I'm sorry
nakitai nakitai nakitai kurai ni
Until we feel like crying and crying
kirei na tsuki no shita uta o utaou
Let's sing a song under the pretty moonlight
donna ni kuradanai sekai datte ii yo
It doesn't matter how awful the world is
setsunai setsunai rarabai kurai ni
Like a sad, sad lullaby
mune ga kurushikute mo hecchara na no sa
even if it hurts inside, it won't bother us
naki sou naki sou naki sou na hodo
Until we're about to cry and cry
yasashii uta datte arun dakara
There will always be a gentle song
Mother loved this world.
She tried to love humans.
But that hope was dashed.
She personally ate
the fruit of the Divine Tree
to try and protect her children.
But real despair started there...
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"Hagoromo and Hamura"
Shortly after,
Mother gave birth to twins.